[MUSIC]
In this lesson I'll talk about how
Android applications can define and
use permissions to control access to
important data, resources and operations.
First, I'll talk about Android's
permissions architecture.
After that,
I'll explain how you can define and
use application level permissions.
And then, I'll finish up by talking about
component specific permissions, and
permissions related APIs.
Android uses permissions to protect
resources, data and operations.
And applications can also define and
enforce their own permissions to limit
access to their resources and
things like user information.
For example, to restrict who can
access an application's database.
To cost sensitive APIs.
For example, to restrict which components
can invoke costly operations such as
sending SMS or MMS messages.
And the system resources, for example,
to limit which components can use
the device's camera to take pictures or
record videos.
So, in Androids,
permissions are represented as strings.
And applications include these permission
strings in the AndroidManifest.xml file.
And they can do this to declare the
permissions that they use themselves and
to declare the permissions that
they require of other components,
that want to use them.
Let's look at each of these uses
of permissions one at a time.
So first, when an application needs to
use a permission, it specifies that
permission by putting a uses-permission
tag in its androidmanifest.xml file.
And when that application
is installed on a device,
the user will have to
accept that permission.
Otherwise errors or
access failures will occur.
Now here I'm showing a snip it of
the androidmanifest.xml file for
a hypothetical application.
Now as you can see, this application needs
permission to access the device's camera,
permission to open a network socket to
access the internet, and permission to
access precise location information,
coming for example from a GPS provider.
Now, take a look at this documentation for
a list of Andriod's built in permissions.
Now you probably remember the map
location from contacts application from
earlier lessons.
That application allows the user to select
a contact from the contacts application,
and then to display a map centered
on that contact's postal address.
So here's the application in action.
Now I'll launch the map location
from contacts application.
Now I see a button that will
allow me to select a contact.
When I click on that button, the contacts
application shows me my contacts and
allows me to select one of them.
Once I do that, that contacts postal
address and other information is passed
to Google Maps which then displays
a map centered on the postal address.
But as I said a few times now,
my contact list is private information.
Android doesn't allow just any application
on my device to have access to
that list of contacts.
So, how did map location from
contacts get access to it?
That's right.
The application must have declared that
it uses the appropriate permission.
And where should we look to confirm that?
Again, that's right, we should look
in the androidmanifest.xml file.
Let's do that now.
So here I've opened up the map location
from contacts application in my IVE.
Now I'll open up
the androidmanifest.xml file.
And we'll take a look inside.
As you can see, there's a uses
permission tag that declares
that this application uses the built
in read_contacts permission.
In addition to declaring
the permissions they use,
Android applications can also define and
enforce their own permissions.
Now suppose that you've written
an application that performs some
privileged or dangerous operation, you
might not want just any application to,
to be able to invoke yours.
So, Android let's you define and enforce
your own application specific permission.
And that means that other applications
must be granted your permission, or
Android will not allow them
to use your application.
Let's look at this in more
detail with a simple example.
So here's a simple application
called Permission Example Boom.
Now we're going to pretend
that it performs some,
some kind of dangerous action.
In real life that might be something like
formatting your external memory card.
Now let's take a look at
this application in action.
Now I'll launch the permission
example Boom application.
And, Boom goes the dynamite.
Now, since this operation,
is clearly dangerous.
We don't want just anyone to be
able to start this application.
So, we're going to define and enforce
our own application specific permission.
Now let's open up the androidmanifest.xml
file to see how that's done.
Here's the permission
example Boom application.
Now I'll open up the androidmanifest.xml
file, and we'll take a look inside.
Here you can see a permissions tag
that defines a new permission.
The permissions name is
course.examples.permissionexample.boom_p-
erm.
In this example the permission tag
includes two other attributes,
a label and a description,
which can be shown to the user when
they are installing the application.
The values for
these strings are in the strings.xml file,
now if we scroll down a bit you can see
that this application also includes this
permission as an attribute
of the application tag.
And because of this, Android will make
sure that components that try to start
this application have already been
granted the boom_perm, permission.
Now since the permission example boom
application now requires
the boom_permission, any other
application wants to use it will first
have to acquire that permission.
So let's see what happens if
an application without the proper
permissions tries to start
PermissionExampleBoom.
So here I'm showing my device and
I've installed a second application on the
device called PermissionExapleBoomUser.
And when I launch this application,
it presents a single
button labelled Detonate.
And if I press this button the Boom User
application will start up the Boom
application, which as I just showed,
requires the boom_perm permission.
The Boom User application, however,
does not have that permission.
So Android should prevent it from
starting up the Boom Application.
Now, before I press the Detonate button,
I'll also point out that I've
opened the IDE and that it's showing
log output from the running device.
Okay, so
now I'll press the detonate button
and as expected something bad
has happened the device is
showing an error dialog telling the user
that the Boom application has stopped.
And if we also go and
look at the log output.
We can get more information as
to the cause of this problem.
And, as you can see in the log,
Android has thrown a security exception,
saying that Boom User
requires the boom_permission.
So, let's fix that problem.
Now, if Boom User wants to
use the Boom application.
Then it has to first declare that
it uses the boom_permission.
To do that, it will put a uses permission
tag in the androidmanifest.xml file.
Let's see that in the code.
So here's the Boom User application code.
And now open up its
andriodManifest.xml file, and
here you can see the uses permission tag,
with a name attribute whose value
is the same as the permission that's
defined by permission example boom.
Okay, so now that we've added
the uses permission tag.
I've reinstalled the permission
boom user application on my device.
So let me go to the home screen and
launch it.
Now there's the Detonate button again and
so
now Ill press it and
Boom goes the dynamite as expected.
So, so far, all the permissions
I've shown you have implied,
have applied the entire application.
Android also allows you to set
permissions for individual components.
And these settings will take precedence
over any application level permissions.
Now let's take a look at some
of these component permissions.
Activity permissions restrict
which components can
start the associated activity.
These permissions are checked
within the execution of methods,
such as start activity, and
start activity for result.
Which, as you you know, are called one
activity tries to start another one.
And if the required permission is missing,
then Android will throw
a security exception.
In fact, that's exactly what happened in
the permissions Boom User example that we
just went over a few seconds ago.
Service permissions restrict
which components can start or
bind to an associated service.
Now, we haven't talked
about services much yet.
So, I'll just mention that permissions,
that these permissions are checked
when requests are made to start,
stop or connect to services.
Using methods such as
Context.startService(),
Context.stopService(), or
Context.bindService().
Just as with activities,
Androids will throw a security exception
if required permissions are missing.
Broadcast receiver permission restrict
which components can send and
receive broadcasts.
Now, again, we haven't talked about
broadcast receivers very much yet.
So, at this point, I'll just say that
these permissions are checked in
a variety of different ways,
at a variety of different times.
And we'll talk more about
this in later lessons when we
discuss broadcast
receivers in more detail.
Content provider permissions,
restrict which components can read and
write the data contained
in a content provider.
And again, we'll talk more about
this in later lessons when we
discuss content providers in more detail.
So, that's all for
this lesson on permissions.
Please join me next time,
when we'll discuss fragments.
Thanks.